<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rootTag>
<Award>
<AwardTitle><![CDATA[MRI: Acquisition of a Single Crystal X-ray Diffractometer at the University of Virginia]]></AwardTitle>
<AGENCY>NSF</AGENCY>
<AwardEffectiveDate>08/15/2020</AwardEffectiveDate>
<AwardExpirationDate>07/31/2023</AwardExpirationDate>
<AwardTotalIntnAmount>273700.00</AwardTotalIntnAmount>
<AwardAmount>273700</AwardAmount>
<AwardInstrument>
<Value>Standard Grant</Value>
</AwardInstrument>
<Organization>
<Code>03090000</Code>
<Directorate>
<Abbreviation>MPS</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Direct For Mathematical &amp; Physical Scien</LongName>
</Directorate>
<Division>
<Abbreviation>CHE</Abbreviation>
<LongName>Division Of Chemistry</LongName>
</Division>
</Organization>
<ProgramOfficer>
<SignBlockName>Amanda Haes</SignBlockName>
<PO_EMAI>ahaes@nsf.gov</PO_EMAI>
<PO_PHON>7032927909</PO_PHON>
</ProgramOfficer>
<AbstractNarration><![CDATA[This award is supported by the Major Research Instrumentation and the Chemistry Research Instrumentation programs. The University of Virginia (UVA) is acquiring a single crystal X-ray diffractometer to support Professor Robert Gilliard and colleagues: Thomas Gunnoe and Diane Dickie. In general, an X-ray diffractometer allows accurate and precise measurements of the full three-dimensional structure of a molecule, including bond distances and angles.  It provides accurate information about the spatial arrangement of a molecule relative to neighboring molecules. The studies described here impact many areas, including organic and inorganic chemistry, materials chemistry and biochemistry. This instrument is an integral part of teaching as well as research and research training of undergraduate and graduate students in chemistry and biochemistry as well as other engineering fields at this institution. In addition, the diffractometer has broad impact on teaching and training, outreach activities, and undergraduate research at UVA. The regional partners from primarily undergraduate institutions (PUIs) have significant female and underrepresented minority populations the also benefit from the use of this instrumentation.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;The award of the X-ray diffractometer is aimed at enhancing research and education at all levels. The instrument acquisition impacts the characterization of synthetic inorganic and organic materials useful to advance manufacturing. The instrumentation is used for studying catalytic processes and using electrochemistry to generate energy relevant products, e.g., conversion of low potential energy chemicals into high energy chemicals for the scaled use of renewable energy sources such as wind, solar. In addition, the diffractometer benefits the exploration of materials chemistry and engineering. It is also used to characterize products relevant to biological chemistry.&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;This award reflects NSF's statutory mission and has been deemed worthy of support through evaluation using the Foundation's intellectual merit and broader impacts review criteria.]]></AbstractNarration>
<MinAmdLetterDate>08/07/2020</MinAmdLetterDate>
<MaxAmdLetterDate>09/07/2022</MaxAmdLetterDate>
<ARRAAmount/>
<TRAN_TYPE>Grant</TRAN_TYPE>
<CFDA_NUM>47.049</CFDA_NUM>
<NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>1</NSF_PAR_USE_FLAG>
<FUND_AGCY_CODE>4900</FUND_AGCY_CODE>
<AWDG_AGCY_CODE>4900</AWDG_AGCY_CODE>
<AwardID>2018870</AwardID>
</Award>
</rootTag>
